Hi!
Now I am going to show you how to repair a rip with a blind stitch.
Okay here is our rip and if you are doing a repair you want to match the thread color to the color of the garment.
Match as closely as possible but for purposes of showing you so that you can exactly what I am doing and what the stitch looks like I am going to use black thread.
That should make it easier for you to see this.
You want to knot your thread like I showed you; nice good knot and we are going to come up from the back of the garment about half an inch from the start of the rip.
You are going to come up from the back to the front of the fabric and then you are going to make the needle go back in just a very small amount like a centimeter and take with the needle only less than a quarter inch, probably eighth of inch of fabric and pull very loosely and then you will go on the opposite side of it; where you came out, you go in and take again about somewhere between a quarter and eighth of fabric like this and then you go directly down from it again and but a little bit wider.
You are going to start very small and close and a little wider, a little wider and you will see what we are going to get.
There you go. Now your stitches start off small, bigger bigger and they are straight up and down perpendicular to the rip; about an eighth of an inch and go in down here.
Now we are up to where the rip begins and we are going to be sewing again just about somewhere between a quarter and eighth of an inch stitches and now we are going to go across the rip and enter here again.
Just about eighth of an inch away from the edge of the rip.
As long as the material isn't fraying and you can put the needle in and it won't be coming out there.
You pull that through.
See how the stitches are coming perpendicular to the rip and let me get a few more and I will show you what to do.
Okay so then once we get a bunch f those, we are going to pull very gently and see how it pulls that rip right together.
It almost looks ike a seam.
So the smaller the stitches, the more delicate the repair will be.